A Guide to the Cathryn Hankla Papers, 1971-1992
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
Cathryn Hankla Papers, 1971-1992
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M 288
9.95 linear feet
Cathryn Hankla
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for use without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
On deposit to Special Collections and Archives. Transfered by Ms. Cathryn Hankla in August of 1992.
Biographical/Historical Information
Cathryn Hankla was born on March 20, 1958 in the Appalachian Mountains in Richlands, VA to Joyce and Alden Hankla. From the age of thirteen her interest in writing was evident as she created a large body of poetry. She continued her interest in writing by working on the school magazine, "Inklings", at Pulaski County High School. After graduating from high school in 1976, she attended Hollins College in Roanoke, Virginia and received a B.A. in English and Film in 1980, and in 1982 she earned a M.A. in English and Creative Writing. Throughout this period she continued to write poetry, short stories, plays, and got married to writer and critic Richard H.W. Dillard in 1979. They were divorced in 1992. Her first book, Phenomena (1983), was reviewed as one of the five best books of poetry published in 1983. Since then she has published a short story anthology, Learning the Mother Tongue (1987), the highly acclaimed novel, A Blue Moon in Poorwater (1988), and another book of poetry Afterimages (1991). Additionally, her reviews, poems, and short stories have appeared in such journals as Yarrow, the Chicago Tribune Sunday Magazine, and College English. Hankla was visiting lecturer in fiction writing at the University of Virginia (spring of 1985), Randolph- Macon's Woman's College Writer in Residence (spring of 1987), and visiting Assistant Professor at Washington and Lee University (1989-1991). Currently, she lives in Troutville, VA and is an associate professor of English at Hollins College (1986-present).
Scope and Content Information
Cathryn Hankla's collection contains her poetry, short stories, plays, and novels from 1971 to 1992. The material documents the development and maturation of Hankla from the age of 13. The bulk of Hankla's collection is in her poetry drafts (1971-1989) and her published work (1980-1992). There are no significant gaps in her collection since its contents are spread out evenly throughout its 21 year period.
Another strength of Hankla's papers is in her poetry. Containing the poems that she has written over a 18 year range, many of her initial poems have been revised repeatedly. These drafts provide an insight to her development as a poet and writer by demonstrating the obvious changes in her style, form, and content. The weakness of this collection is the lack of any biographical information about Cathryn Hankla. Except for some passing information in some of her book reviews, there is no significant information about Hankla herself.
In this collection of novels, poetry, short stories, plays, theses, and notes, a large area of interest is in her published work. This is especially true in examples like Phenomena, Learning the Mother Tongue, A Blue Moon in Poorwater, and Afterimages that contain a complete set of correspondence, drafts, and reviews. Specifically, the correspondence shows her initial contact with numerous publishing companies and her continuous discussion with the eventual publisher about the evolution of her work. As a result, the collection documents the complete development of her work from draft to review. Presently, Hankla is not represented in any other repository.
Arrangement
Arrangement
Collection is arranged chronologically.
Organization
The collection is a result of a single accession. Artificial series were imposed on the collection to highlight the development of Hankla's work. Series 1 was divided into two subseries and chronologically arranged therein from oldest to newest, while Series 2,3, 5-7 were arranged chronologically as well. In Series 4 there were eight subseries with correspondence arranged chronologically and placed at the beginning. Drafts are arranged chronologically, and reviews follow the drafts. Researchers must note that within the collection there are places where documents from one series could be placed in another if it were not for the fact that two different works shared a piece of paper. Also, it must be noted that "First Person Love" has not been published yet.
Contents List
- Poetry, n.d. 1971-1989
  - Poetry Drafts, n.d. 1971-1989
    - Poetry, n.d. 1971-1974 (Box-folder 1.1)
    - Poetry, n.d. 1973-1974 (Box-folder 1.2)
    - Poetry, n.d. 1973-1975 (Box-folder 1.3)
    - Poetry, n.d. 1974-1976 (Box-folder 1.4)
    - Poetry, n.d. 1975 (Box-folder 1.5)
    - Poetry, n.d. 1975-1976 (Box-folder 1.6)
    - Poetry, n.d. 1976 (Box-folder 1.7)
    - Poetry (1 of 9), n.d. 1979-1989 (Box-folder 1.8)
    - Poetry (2 of 9), n.d. 1979-1989 (Box-folder 2.1)
    - Poetry (3 of 9), n.d. 1979-1989 (Box-folder 2.2)
    - Poetry (4 of 9), n.d. 1979-1989 (Box-folder 2.3)
    - Poetry (5 of 9), n.d. 1979-1989 (Box-folder 2.4)
    - Poetry (6 of 9), n.d. 1979-1989 (Box-folder 2.5)
    - Poetry (7 of 9), n.d. 1979-1989 (Box-folder 2.6)
    - Poetry (8 of 9), n.d. 1979-1989 (Box-folder 3.1)
    - Poetry (9 of 9), n.d. 1979-1989 (Box-folder 3.2)
    - Poetry, n.d. 1981-1988 (Box-folder 3.3)
    - Poetry 1974-1975 (Box-folder 3.4)
    - Poetry: Hankla Endeavors 1974-1975 (Box-folder 3.5)
    - Poetry (1 of 2) 1974-1976 (Box-folder 3.6)
    - Poetry (2 of 2) 1974-1976 (Box-folder 3.7)
    - Poetry 1976-1977 (Box-folder 3.8)
  - Poetry Manuscripts, n.d. 1982-1983
    - Poetry Manuscript: Persistence of Vision, n.d. (Box-folder 4.1)
    - Poetry Manuscript: The Tautology of Goodbye, n.d. (Box-folder 4.2)
    - Poetry Manuscript: Tree in the Rock, n.d. (1 of 4) (Box-folder 4.3)
    - Poetry Manuscript: The Juggler's Ghost and Other Poems(2 of 4), n.d. 1982-1983 (Box-folder 4.4)
    - Poetry Manuscript: Vanishing Islands, n.d. (3 of 4) 1982-1983 (Box-folder 4.5)
    - Poetry Manuscript, n.d. (4 of 4) (Box-folder 4.6)
- Short Stories and Plays, n.d. 1980-1988
  - Short Stories, n.d. (Box-folder 4.7)
  - Short Stories: The Cartoonist, n.d. 1982 (Box-folder 4.8)
  - Short Stories: The Life of An American No One, n.d. (Box-folder 4.9)
  - Short Stories: Marks of the Prism, n.d. (Box-folder 4.10)
  - Short Stories, n.d. 1980-1982, 1984, 1988 (1 of 4) (Box-folder 5.1)
  - Short Stories, n.d. 1980-1982, 1984, 1988 (Box-folder 5.2)
  - Short Stories, n.d. 1980-1982, 1984, 1988 (Box-folder 5.3)
  - Short Stories, n.d. 1980-1982, 1984, 1988 (Box-folder 5.4)
  - Play Manuscript: Disintegration: A Libretto, n.d. (Box-folder 5.5)
  - Play Manuscript: The Pier as Breakwater, n.d. (Box-folder 5.6)
  - Play Manuscript: Drop Dead Twice, n.d. 1982 (Box-folder 5.7)
  - Play Manuscript: Disintegration: A Libretto, n.d. 1982 (Box-folder 5.8)
  - Play Manuscript: The Pier as Breakwater, n.d. 1982 (Box-folder 5.9)
- Published Work, n.d. 1980-1992
  - Book Review, n.d. 1981, 1984, 1985, 1987
    - Book Reviews, n.d. 1981, 1984, 1985, 1987 (Box-folder 6.1.)
  - A Wilderness of Light, n.d.
    - Manuscript, n.d. (Box-folder 6.2)
  - Phenomena, n.d. 1980-1986
    - Correspondences 1980-1983 (Box-folder 6.3)
    - Manuscript 1981 (Box-folder 6.4)
    - Manuscript 1981 (Box-folder 6.4)
    - Edited Manuscript 1982 (Box-folder 6.5)
    - Reviews, n.d. 1981-1984 (Box-folder 6.6)
    - Congratulations, n.d. 1983-1986 (Box-folder 6.7)
  - Fiction/86, n.d. 1987
    - Reviews, n.d. 1983 (Box-folder 6.8)
  - Learning the Mother Tongue, n.d. 1985-1987
    - Correspondences 1985-1987 (Box-folder 7.1)
    - Manuscript, n.d.(1 of 2) (Box-folder 7.2)
    - Manuscript, n.d. (2 of 2) (Box-folder 7.3)
    - Reviews 1987-1988 (Box-folder 7.4)
    - Congratulations 1985-1987 (Box-folder 7.5)
  - A Blue Moon in Poorwater, n.d. 1985-1988
    - Correspondences 1985-1988 (Box-folder 7.6)
    - Notes and Misc., n.d. 1983, 1985, 1986 (Box-folder 7.7)
    - Original Manuscript, n.d. (1 of 3) (Box-folder 7.8)
    - Original Manuscript, n.d. (2 of 3) (Box-folder 7.9)
    - Original Manuscript, n.d. (3 of 3) (Box-folder 8.1)
    - Proofed Manuscript, n.d. (1 of 4) (Box-folder 8.2)
    - Proofed Manuscript, n.d. (2 of 4) (Box-folder 8.3)
    - Proofed Manuscript, n.d. (3 of 4) (Box-folder 8.4)
    - Proofed Manuscript, n.d. (4 of 4) (Box-folder 8.5)
    - Proofed Manuscript (1 of 2) (Box-folder 8.5)
    - Proofed Manuscript (1 of 2) 1985 (Box-folder 8.6)
    - Proofed Manuscript (2 of 2) (Box-folder 8.7)
    - Copy of Proofed Manuscript (1 of 2) 1985 (Box-folder 9.1)
    - Copy of Proofed Manuscript (2 of 2) 1985 (Box-folder 9.2)
    - Manuscript with revision notes, n.d. (1 of 3) 1986 (Box-folder 9.3)
    - Manuscript with revision notes, n.d. (2 of 3) 1986 (Box-folder 9.4)
    - Manuscript with revision notes, n.d. (3 of 3) (Box-folder 9.5)
    - Author's 1st Proof (1 of 2) 1987 (Box-folder 9.6)
    - Author's 1st Proof (2 of 2) 1987 (Box-folder 9.7)
    - Copy of Author's 1st Proof (1 of 2) 1987 (Box-folder 10.1)
    - Copy of Author's 1 st Proof (2 of 2) 1987 (Box-folder 10.2)
    - Uncorrected Proof 1988 (Box-folder 10.3)
    - Reviews (1 of 2) 1988-1989 (Box-folder 10.4)
    - Reviews (2 of 2) 1988-1989 (Box-folder 10.5)
  - Afterimages, n.d. 1990-1992
    - Correspondences 1990-1992 (Box-folder 10.6)
    - Manuscript, n.d. (Box-folder 10.7)
    - 1st Proof, n.d. (Box-folder 11.1)
    - 2nd Proof, n.d. (Box-folder 11.2)
    - Reviews 1991-1992 (Box-folder 11.3)
  - First Person Love(Magical Thorn: An Affliction of Love), n.d. 1984-1991
    - Correspondences 1990-1991 (Box-folder 11.4)
    - Notes and Misc., n.d. (Box-folder 11.5)
    - Notes and Misc., n.d. 1984-1985, 1989 (Box-folder 11.6)
    - Early Draft, n.d. 1986, 1989 (Box-folder 11.7)
    - Draft, n.d. (1 of 2) (Box-folder 11.8)
    - Draft, n.d. (2 of 2) (Box-folder 11.9)
    - Draft, n.d. (1 of 3) (Box-folder 12.1)
    - Draft, n.d. (2 of 3) (Box-folder 12.2)
    - Draft, n.d. (3 of 3) (Box-folder 12.3)
    - Draft, n.d. (1 of 6) 1991 (Box-folder 12.4)
    - Draft, n.d. (2 of 6) 1991 (Box-folder 12.5)
    - Draft, n.d. (3 of 6) 1991 (Box-folder 13.1)
    - Draft, n.d. (4 of 6) 1991 (Box-folder 13.2)
    - Draft, n.d. (5 of 6) 1991 (Box-folder 13.3)
    - Draft, n.d. (5 of 6) 1991 (Box-folder 13.4)
    - Final Draft, n.d. (1 of 2) (Box-folder 13.5)
    - Final Draft, n.d. (2 of 2) (Box-folder 13.6)
- Writing Notes, n.d. 1979-1984
  - On Work, n.d. 1979-1984
    - Work, n.d. (Box-folder 14.1)
    - Work, n.d. (Box-folder 14.2)
    - Work, n.d. (Box-folder 14.3)
    - Work, n.d. (Box-folder 14.4)
    - Work, n.d. (Box-folder 14.5)
    - Work, n.d. 1984 (Box-folder 14.6)
    - Work 1979-1981 (Box-folder 14.7)
    - Work 1980 (Box-folder 14.8)
- College Thesis, n.d. 1980-1982
  - Drafts, n.d.
    - Draft, n.d. (Box-folder 14.9)
  - Manuscripts 1980-1982
    - Honors English: Things in Their Times 1980 (Box-folder 14.10)
    - Masters in English Writing: Some Real and Imaginary Animals 1982 (Box-folder 14.11)
- Publications 1972-1992
  - Alchemy 1981 (Box 15)
  - Artemis 1977 (Box 15)
  - Artemis 1978 (Box 15)
  - Artemis 1979 (Box 15)
  - Artemis 1980 (Box 15)
  - Artemis 1982 (Box 15)
  - Artemis 1983 (Box 15)
  - Artemis VIII 1984 (Box 15)
  - Artemis 1987 (Box 15)
  - Artemis 1988 (Box 15)
  - Artemis XII 1989 (Box 15)
  - The Best of Intro 1985 (Box 15)
  - Black Warrior Review 1981 (Box 15)
  - Cargoes 1976 (Box 15)
  - Cargoes 1977 (Box 15)
  - Cargoes 1978 (Box 15)
  - Cargoes 1978 (Box 15)
  - Cargoes 1979 (Box 15)
  - Cargoes 1979 (Box 15)
  - Cargoes 1979 (Box 15)
  - Cargoes 1980 (Box 15)
  - Cargoes 1980 (Box 15)
  - Cargoes 1981 (Box 15)
  - Cargoes 1989 (Box 15)
  - The Chattahoochee Review 1986 (Box 15)
  - College English 1991 (Box 15)
  - Contemporary Southern Short Fiction 1990 (Box 15)
  - Creation Four 1972 (Box 15)
  - Creation Five 1973 (Box 15)
  - Creation Six 1974 (Box 15)
  - Dan River Anthology 1985 (Box 15)
  - Dan River Anthology 1985 (Box 15)
  - Denver Quarterly 1986 (Box 15)
  - The Devil's Millhopper 1981 (Box 15)
  - Fiction/86 1986 (Box 15)
  - Helicon Nine 1983 (Box 15)
  - Images 1984 (Box 15)
  - Images 1986 (Box 15)
  - Images 1986 (Box 15)
  - Images 1986 (Box 15)
  - Images 1986 (Box 15)
  - Inklings 1975 (Box 15)
  - Inklings 1976 (Box 15)
  - Inklings 1976 (Box 15)
  - Intro 10 1979 (Box 15)
  - Intro 11 1980 (Box 15)
  - Intro 13 1982 (Box 15)
  - Mid-American Review 1981 (Box 15)
  - The Missouri Review 1982 (Box 15)
  - MVR 1982 (Box 15)
  - MVR 1984 (Box 15)
  - New Jersey Poetry Journal 1981 (Box 15)
  - New Jersey Poetry Journal 1983 (Box 15)
  - New Jersey Poetry Journal 1985 (Box 15)
  - New Virginia Review 1986 (Box 15)
  - New Virginia Review 1988 (Box 16)
  - Outerbridge 1980-1981 (Box 16)
  - Outerbridge 1983-1984 (Box 16)
  - Passages North 1981 (Box 16)
  - Passages North 1981 (Box 16)
  - Ploughshares 1983 (Box 16)
  - Ploughshares 1983 (Box 16)
  - Quarterly West 1981-1982 (Box 16)
  - Shenandoah 1988 (Box 16)
  - Shenandoah 1989 (Box 16)
  - Sunday 1989 (Box 16)
  - Telescope 1983 (Box 16)
  - The Texas Review 1984 (Box 16)
  - The Texas Review 1984 (Box 16)
  - Thicket 1978 (Box 16)
  - The Third Log 1986 (Box 16)
  - Vital Signs 1989 (Box 16)
  - Webster Review 1984 (Box 16)
  - Window 1978 (Box 16)
  - World and I 1992 (Box 16)
  - World and I 1992 (Box 16)
  - Yarrow 1985 (Box 16)
  - Yarrow 1988 (Box 16)
  - Yarrow 1990-1991 (Box 16)
  - Afterimages: Folder 11.2 2nd Proof, n.d., oversized (Box 17)